<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Civil wars of Bantam, or, An Impartial relation of all the battels, sieges, and other remarkable transactions, revolutions and accidents that happened in the late civil wars between that king and his eldest son, commonly called by them, the young king : giving a particular account of the circumstances and manner of the siege and taking of the city of Bantam, and the English factory there, by the young king, with the help and assistance of the Dutch / in several letters from a gentleman residing for the East-India-Company at Bantam, to a merchant in London.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33200</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4366A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43100</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">26813815</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 26813815</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109803</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33200)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109803)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1713:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Civil wars of Bantam, or, An Impartial relation of all the battels, sieges, and other remarkable transactions, revolutions and accidents that happened in the late civil wars between that king and his eldest son, commonly called by them, the young king : giving a particular account of the circumstances and manner of the siege and taking of the city of Bantam, and the English factory there, by the young king, with the help and assistance of the Dutch / in several letters from a gentleman residing for the East-India-Company at Bantam, to a merchant in London.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H.C. for Tho. Malthus at the sign of the Sun in the Poultrey,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXIII. [1683]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 18.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Indonesia --  History --  1478-1798.</term>
               <term>Bantam (Jawa Barat, Indonesia) --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109803:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CIVIL WARS OF BANTAM: OR, AN Impartial Relation OF ALL THE BATTELS, SIEGES, and other Remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able TRANSACTIONS, REVOLUTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONS and ACCIDENTS that happened in the late <hi>Civil Wars</hi> BETWEEN THAT KING AND HIS ELDEST SON, COMMONLY CALLED BY THEM, <hi>The Young King,</hi> GIVING A Particular Account of the Circumstances and Manner of the Siege and taking of the City of <hi>Bantam,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh Factory</hi> there, by the Young King, with the Help and Aſſiſtance of the <hi>Dutch;</hi> In ſeveral Letters from a Gentleman Reſiding for the <hi>East-India-</hi>Company at <hi>Bantam,</hi> to a Merchant in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by H. C. for <hi>Tho. Malthus</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Sun</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> MDCLXXXIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:109803:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109803:2"/>
            <head>THE CIVIL WARRS OF BANTAM: OR, An Impartial Relation of all the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, Sieges, and other Remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Tranſactions, Resolutions and Accidents which happened in the late Wars between the KING and His Eldeſt SON, Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Called by them, The YOUNG KING.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Sudden and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nexpected Breach which hath happened here, between the King of <hi>Bantam</hi> and His Eldeſt Son; together with the conſiderable Dammage which the <hi>Engliſh Merchants</hi> have ſustained thereby, in the Loſs of their Factory, and a good part of their Trade, hath been Matter of much Wonder and Amazement to us
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:109803:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>here; and (I ſuppoſe) no leſs, but rather much more to you in <hi>England:</hi> which doth (I imagine) render you deſirous to learn the Occaſion and Manner of it; which I herewith ſend you, hoping it will give you full Satisfaction; for although to be preſent at, and be a Sufferer in the Extremities of War, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Calamities which always attend the Beſieging and Storming of Cities, yet the hearing thereof at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, or the reading the written Relations of it, uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally afford abundance of Pleaſure and Delight eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when there is any thing extraordinary in the Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or in the Manner of Proſecuting and Managing the War: ſomewhat of both which you will find in the following Relation.</p>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Bantam,</hi> 
                     <date>March 16. 1681/2</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>THE 11th. Inſtant, this Ship was in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs To Sail, but was retarded by the King of <hi>Bantam</hi>'s Letter to His Majeſty of <hi>England,</hi> it not being ready till the 13<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> when at Midnight he ſent it on Board. The next Morning, by Break of Day, the <hi>Dutch</hi> with Sloops and ſmall Boats attempted to Land their Men at the Rivers Mouth (which is about a Musket-Shot diſtant from our Factory) ſo that we could not ſend off our Diſpatch.</p>
               <p>They lay there all that day, and the <hi>Javas</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my cloſe by them, who had poſitive Orders from the King of <hi>Bantam,</hi> not to begin firſt.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Dutch</hi> durſt not venture farther, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a great Number of Men ready to oppoſe them,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109803:3"/>with far greater Courage than they (or indeed we our ſelves) did expect; towards Break of Day yeſterday, the Water flowing, and their Veſſels off the Ground, they all repaired thereto, and ſtood a little diſtance from the Rivers Mouth; when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Nine of the Clock in the Morning, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan the War with their great Guns from their great Ships and Hulks that were moored with their Broad-Sides to the Shoar, for the ſaid purpoſe; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Firing as faſt as ever they could till after Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet:</p>
               <p>The <hi>Javas</hi> manfully kept the Shoar the whole day without much loſs of Men, and fired ſeveral great Guns from the Walls, ſome of which did exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution on their Ships; and the <hi>Dutch</hi> this Morning have drawn all their ſmall Veſſels from the Shoar, We are in hopes all their future Attempts will be in vain; the <hi>Javas</hi> manifeſting a reſolute Intention of defying them, rather than come under their Yoke, and are not a little animated with Courage, to ſee the <hi>Dutch</hi> retreat.</p>
               <p>Our Factory ſtanding in harms way, we receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed great Shot in abundance; my own, and ſeveral others Chambers, each receiving one: But God be thanked, not a Soul in them hurt: We believe the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſent many of them, knowing our Nation to have ſupplied this King with moſt of his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, and to animate to our power the <hi>Javas</hi> againſt them: whereby we may partly gueſs the Kindneſs they will ſhew us if they come on Shoar. Their Fleet remains ſtill in Harbor, and whether they will attempt further, none knows; we are bound to ſee the Event; and I hope, happen the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109803:4"/>worſt, we ſhall ſave our Lives. <hi>Sir,</hi> I thought it expedient to give you this Account, though the Bearer can ſatisfie you more largely; yet for what paſſed on Shoar, he has it himſelf by hear-ſay.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours, <hi>S. G.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Batavia,</hi> 
                     <date>September 17. 1682.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I wrote you two Letters by the <hi>Scipio African;</hi> and in that of the later Date, adviſed more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly the Condition we were then in; which I ſhall not repeat, but continue the Doleful Subject to the preſent time.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Dutch</hi> the Morning before her Departure, being oppoſed Landing, reſted quiet in their Ships till the 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>March;</hi> when, before Day, with a freſh Supply of Forces, they Landed half a Mile diſtant from our Factory, ſoon Routed all the <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vas,</hi> and received a welcom Admiſſion into the Fort of the Young King (then drove to ſo great a ſtreight by the Siege of his Fathers Army, that he could not have held out many days longer, and that with the loſs of not above forty or fifty Men) they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately hoyſed their Standard, and what remain'd undeſtroyed by the Old King's Forces, they that day moſtly burnt, and Marched in Triumph through every part of the Town: We kept our Factory Gates ſhut, and were by them unmoleſted; as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the <hi>French, Danes</hi> and <hi>Chineſes:</hi> But the ſame
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109803:4"/>Evening, about Five of the Clock, after we had ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laced our ſelves with hopes of Security, a Report was ſpread abroad that the Young King deſign'd to cut us all off that very Night, being incenſed at the conceived Aſſiſtance of Men and Ammunition afforded his Father by us during his being beſieged; and thereupon, moſt of the <hi>Chineſes,</hi> who had for the ſecurity of their eſtates, brought great part thereof into our Factory, like ſo many Bees flocked about us, to take the ſame out.</p>
               <p>It was Night, and we had only on ſmall Ships Boat on ſhoar, ſo we were neceſſitated to ſtand the event; and ſent her to give notice thereof to our Ships, with Orders to looſe their Sails, get their Anchors apeak, and be gone, and if we were aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted, to give Tidings what became of us; not a man of us departing the Shoar that belonged to the Factory; then we put our ſelves in a poſture of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, hoping, without the Aſſiſtance of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> to make our part good againſt all the People the Young King had; dividing our ſelves into two Watches, my Lot being in the firſt.</p>
               <p>After Midnight, I went to Reſt with ſomewhat better Hopes than thoſe that had the firſt Sleep; as conceiving, if they had any real Design upon us, we ſhould have heard of it before that time.</p>
               <p>Repoſe made the remaining hours ſhort; and the firſt Salute to my waking eyes, was the Glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Day; when by a Sign (as appointed) with our Flag, the Ships Boats came on ſhoar; and ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Dutch</hi> Chief from the <hi>Fort,</hi> with a File of Souldiers, and ſeveral Carpenters came to their <hi>Factory,</hi> into the Yard whereof we had two
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109803:5"/>Galleries and ſeveral Windows, acquainting us in the moſt imperious manner he could expreſs himſelf, That it was the King's Order to cut down the one, and ſtop up the other; which if we did not imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately do, his People ſhould: An Action of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Inſultation and Spite, deſign'd to increaſe our Fears and Amazement; their Factory being at that time uninhabited, and indeed almoſt ruined; yet we were forced to comply: The ſaid Chief having lived many years in <hi>Bantam,</hi> and been our intimate Companion, induced us to believe his Moroſity might be the effect of his Superiors Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and that from him we might poſſibly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Reality of the reported Maſſacre the night before, and whether ſtill deſign'd; therefore was my ſelf ſent down to him, who told me it was really in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and a going to have been put in execution by the young King, but by their Major he was hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and diſwaded therefrom; which, though we believe a Truth, yet next to the Divine Mercy, we can impute it only to the (by them feared) ill Conſequences, who by reaſon of the ſmall number of the King's People, could not have acquitted themſelves of being acceſſary thereto, if not by their Aſſiſtance, at leaſt by their Permiſſion, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as it was they that incens'd him againſt us, by their aggravating all our Actions what poſſibly they could to our Diſadvantage.</p>
               <p>Upon this we reſolved, and accordingly went to the King, to congratulate his ſafe Delivery out of his late Troubles, that if he had any thing to ſay to us, we might clear our ſelves: Before whom,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109803:5"/>when come, we found no ſuch angry Aſpect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his brow, as by what was reported to us, we had reaſon to expect; he reproached us with our aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Father, contrary to our <hi>Engagement</hi> of ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Neuter; and what moſt <hi>aggravated,</hi> was, that three of our Company came the day before the <hi>Landing</hi> of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> to the Camp, cloſe under his Wall, to inſtruct his Fathers Souldiers how to plant their Great Guns againſt him; I was my felf one in perſon, with Mr. <hi>George Chowne,</hi> then of Council, and Mr. <hi>Rich. Burnby,</hi> formerly Chief of <hi>Siam,</hi> who went, (as we acquainted him) only out of curioſity to ſee the place, upon an Invitation of the Captain that lay there; and as a proof of our Innocency and unthought of giving occaſion of Diſpleaſure or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt of his Majeſty, we came within Call of his Soldiers on the Wall, without any other defence, ſave our confidence that we not medling or making on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, they would not hurt us (but it ſhall be a warning to me for ever expoſing my ſelf to ſo great a danger upon any ſuch like Conſiderations ſo long as I live) and that what Supplies we otherwiſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded his Father, we were neceſſitated to, as being wholly under his Power, and himſelf then incloſed in his Fort, and unable to protect us. He interpreted all as excuſes, acquainting us that tho' it was in his power to cut us off, yet out of that reſpect he had to our King and Company, would deſiſt therefrom; a Leſſon learnt him by the <hi>Dutch.</hi> Being diſmiſt, we were the 31<hi rend="sup">ſt</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly affrighted with his Men in Arms, coming to our <hi>Factory,</hi> under the conduct of one or other of his three great Miniſters of State he had left him, or a <hi>Dutch</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negado, by him highly advanced, whom we knew not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109803:6"/>how to truſt, neither durſt deny Admittance; when in the evening, the Chief of the ſaid Miniſters, he that has been above two years underhand with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> contriving to bring the Deſign about of get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Bantam,</hi> came to us with a Paper written in the <hi>Mallay</hi> Language, ſaid to be ſent us from the King; being an Order to us, with all poſſible ſpeed to get our Goods aboard our Ships, and depart his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; he preſſing us to the moſt ſpeedy compliance poſſible therewith, as we ſtood in awe of the Kings Diſpleaſure.</p>
               <p>We were ſince informed that there was a great Diſpute between the King and the <hi>Dutch</hi> Major, before he could be brought to Order us out of his Countrey, well conſidering how great a Support to, and Inrichment of his Kingdom our Trade had been: But being wholly under the <hi>Dutch</hi> Power, he was forced to comply, and we to his Commands; and ſo purpoſed with all poſſible ſpeed to get off our Goods, and depart for <hi>Batavia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But our Ships being moſt of them nigh full, we were neceſſitated to requeſt a Ship of near five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Tuns, of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Major, to export them; ſo the next Morning we wrote a Letter to him, which we ſent by four of the Companies Servants, to deliver; who coming to the <hi>Fort,</hi> the Captain of the Guard told them he was aſleep: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they left it with him, and returned home.</p>
               <p>But whilſt we were expecting of an Anſwer, the ſame evening comes to us the aboveſaid Miniſter and Votary to the <hi>Dutch,</hi> with the ſaid Letter unopen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſeating himſelf at the upper end of our Table, and filling our Great Hall with his followers, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109803:6"/>for Mr. <hi>Barwell,</hi> and ſome others of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, who coming before him, he takes forth the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and tells us with Rage, the <hi>King</hi> had ſent him to know the meaning of that Papers being found on the Ground under the <hi>Fort</hi>-Walls, <hi>aggravating</hi> it as a Cauſe of the higheſt Suſpition, now in time of War; and when we had told him what it was, and laboured to make him ſenſible that it was our <hi>Europe</hi> Cuſtom to ſignifie our Minds in Writing, and that our Meaning therein was moſt innocent, he replied, he admired how we durſt preſume to write to the Major without firſt acquainting the <hi>King;</hi> and all this with ſo much Paſſion and Fury, that nothing could look more like a Prologue to a Maſſacre; till at length he mildly adviſed us the next morning to go and ask the <hi>King</hi>'s Pardon.</p>
               <p>Many other Circumſtances of Amazement in this Buſineſs did paſs, too tedious to repreſent: But by what we have ſaid, you may <hi>imagine</hi> the baſeneſs of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who were the whole Contrivers and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of this Buſineſs, as did plainly appear by that Letter being delivered into their hands, and the <hi>King</hi>'s not <hi>mentioning</hi> one word to us about it, the next <hi>Morning,</hi> notwithſtanding we never offered to ask him Pardon.</p>
               <p>But this is but little to their <hi>ſucceeding Treatments,</hi> as you will ſee by what follows: That day we had ſent off two of our Ships Boats full of <hi>Broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloath,</hi> which without the Rivers Mouth were fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by a <hi>Dutch</hi> Pinnace, <hi>ordering,</hi> them <hi>back again,</hi> or elſe they would fire at them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Their Return ſurprized us; but not knowing but its being late at night, might be the occaſion, we ſent them
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109803:7"/>again the next morning, when they were again ſtopped by the</hi> Dutch <hi>Souldiers quartering a little below our Facto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, who told us they had Orders to ſuffer no loaden Boat of ours to go out of the River: we complained to the Major, who told us it was the King's Order; who, alas poor man! had ſo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n-King'd himſelf, that he could Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand no further than ſtood with the Pleaſure of the</hi> Dutch; <hi>but many hours did not paſs before we underſtood the depth of the Deſign, by one</hi> Jacob de Roy, <hi>a Lieutenant in the</hi> Dutch <hi>Army, who had been with the King all the time of his being beſieged in the Fort, coming ſome few Months before, under pretence of being a Baker to</hi> Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, <hi>who brought us a Charge of about ten thouſand Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als</hi> 8/8 <hi>for Jewels and Plate of his in the</hi> Dutch <hi>Factory, which at the time of the Old King's entering the Town, he ſaid we had plundered and taken into ours, which till we ſatisfied, none of our Goods ſhould be permitted to go on board, where by the way, you may obſerve, firſt, their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign ſo far to amaze and affright us, that we might upon any Terms be willing to leave the ſhoar; and then having ſo prepared us, to enrich themſelves with the Companies and our Eſtate. Indeed this Buſineſs at that time ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led us, and made us very thoughtful concerning them, much fearing ſome ill Deſignes upon us, we laboured by Preſents to the King's Miniſters, to learn the depth of the Deſign, and divert it; but in concluſion found them too much the</hi> Dutch <hi>Votaries, to be our Friends: inſomuch that we were wholly to ſeek what to do: Whilſt to perplex us yet further, comes a Meſſage to us, that the King was jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of our aſſiſting his Fathers Boats with Powder from our Ship in the Road, therefore deſired us to deliver up all on Board them, which, when we departed, ſhould be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully reſtored.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:109803:7"/>
               <p>We replied, That when we delivered our Powder, we delivered our Ships, they being without it whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defenceleſs, therefore would upon no Terms do it, but would our ſelves go ſpeak with the King, which accordingly we did; when coming into his preſence were prevented ſaying any thing to him, he immediately ſending for a Letter wrote in <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugueze</hi> and directed to the Engliſh as from one of the Old Kings Sons, which he ordered to be read to us; the Contents were, That we the <hi>French</hi> the <hi>Danes,</hi> and the <hi>Portugueze,</hi> ſhould at a certain time be in readineſs for their Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but where or how, we knew not; which he aggravated highly againſt us, not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to ſpeak in our defence, or to ſay any thing concerning the ſtoppage of our Goods, or our Powder being demanded out of our Ships, and bid us be gone; from whom being departed, we went to the Dutch Major, making known our Grievance to him, who ſmilling, told us, All was by Order of the King, though done by their Souldiers, and ſeem'd ignorant of the Letter, tho nothing more probable than that it was of their own framing; and promiſed in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Terms to aſſiſt us to his power: ſo took our leaves, and being return'd to our Factory, we heard the <hi>Portugueze</hi> Ship was ſeized on by the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Javas</hi> together, with an Account of the ſaid Letter, and that the <hi>French</hi> had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of her of theirs 4 Cheſts of Money, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put the ſame on board of her for ſecurity in the time of the Siege: And that the aforeſaid
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109803:8"/>
                  <hi>Jacob de Roy</hi> with ſome other Souldiers of the <hi>Dutch</hi> and Kings, went to the Honourable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies Ship the <hi>Tywan Frigat,</hi> acquainting the Commander they had Orders to ſearch for Powder; who telling them they had none, neither could permit thereof without Orders from us aſhore: They were about to enter the Ship, he immediately gave the word for his Men to ſtand to their Arms, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they deſiſted, gave him good words, and deſired that only <hi>Jacob de Roy</hi> and one <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va</hi> Man, might be permitted to look between Decks for ſatisfaction of the King, which being granted they departed. This News I ſay, with our Treatment with the King and Major, ſeem'd almoſt to confirm to us ſome evil Deſigns, if not upon our Lives, at leaſt upon the Companies and our Eſtates. But it being no time to ſit ſtill, we concluded immediately to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch away the <hi>Formoſa Frigat</hi> (a ſmall Ship of the Companies) to <hi>Batavia,</hi> to make our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints to the General and Council there, but chiefly to ſecure the Honourable Companies Treaſure, which was the thing they ſeem'd to gape at, My ſelf and Mr. <hi>George Chowne</hi> were ſent upon her, and indeed it was our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to go, having had notice that the King had been ſolicited by the <hi>Dutch Renegado</hi> (a Villain fitted for the worſt of Actions) to come to our Factory and kill us in particular, upon account of our being ſeen in his Enemies Camp at the time of his being beſieged; to which altho he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109803:8"/>declin'd condiſcending, who knew what the importunity of ſuch a Villain in time might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to. We departed the Shore in a ſmall Boat, about <hi>half an hour</hi> before Sun ſet, with Order for all the Companies Treaſure on board the Companies other Ships, to be put on board her in the dark, and with the ſmalleſt noiſe poſſible to weigh <hi>Anchor,</hi> leſt we ſhould have been diſcovered by the <hi>Dutch Ships.</hi> There ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied us the Agents Lady, Mr. <hi>Thomas James</hi> late Chief of <hi>Tonkeene,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rich. Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Samuel Griffith,</hi> who being out of the Company's Service, had kept themſelves aboard Ship for their ſecurity, which made our paſſage ſeem ſhorter, being of it ſelf a little long, even four days, before we arrived at <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavia,</hi> where Mr. <hi>George Chowne</hi> the ſame day we arrived died: I went to the General, and was appointed the next day to be heard; when being admitted before him and all the Lords ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in Council, I made a Relation of our Treatments at <hi>Bantam,</hi> requeſting a Ship of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 500 Tons Burthen, for the Exportation of our Goods, and their Orders to their people there, to permit them to be brought off; with their permiſſion to hire an houſe in <hi>Batavia,</hi> and land our Goods, to Export them as we had occaſion, Cuſtom free; to all which we received then lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reply, being deferred for Anſwer till next day, when another of the Honourable Companies Ships, to wit, the <hi>Returne,</hi> arriv'd with Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Barwell,</hi> to whoſe turn by lot it came to come away (ſo willing were all the Gentlemen
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109803:9"/>left there of Council to come away, that they could no other ways agree who ſhould) the <hi>Dutch</hi> at <hi>Bantam</hi> not having any of our Goods at his departure to be brought off. And their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings being ſuch, under Colour of the Kings Orders, as forced our people to take care to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure what Eſtate the Company had already off the Shore, he and I again waited on the General, who told us, That we might hire an Houſe where we pleas'd, that he would order a Ship or two, if occaſion was, by the firſt opportunity; as likewiſe, that our Goods ſhould be all ſafely brought avvay, and for vvhat vve had further requeſted, vvould after they had debated it, give Anſvver: But before his Order reached <hi>Bantam,</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> there ſeeing two of our Ships gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in the Night time, and imagining in them to be the chiefeſt Treaſure, permitted them to load the other ſmall one and Sloop there remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, putting the King upon haſtening our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple away, with all ſpeed imaginable, ſeizing all the Proviſions in the Factory, that they were forced to live the day before they left the Shore upon the Charity of the <hi>Chineſs.</hi> And on the 12th of <hi>April</hi> arrived here the <hi>Tywan Frigat,</hi> vvith all our People from <hi>Bantam,</hi> except one Factor, who as if by miſtake ſtayed behind to have an Eye to their Actions. At their departure they ſealed up all the Companies Ware-houſes, leaving a Regiſter of their Effects and Factory (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as near as vve could gueſs about the value of 22000 <hi>Royals of Eight</hi>) vvith one of the <hi>Dutch
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109803:9"/>Commiſsioners</hi> to be delivered, the Major being here arrived, the General deſired us, to ſend back in their Ships three or four Factors to take care of the Shipping of our Goods, which was done accordingly, but in ſo confus'd a manner, as what the <hi>Dutch</hi> pleaſed to reſtore us, we can on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call ours: So ended the Honourable Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies antient Factory of <hi>Bantam,</hi> where the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh have been ſettled, and have had a conſtant Trade about this 70 years. I cannot ſay they departed thence like <hi>Hannibal</hi> out of <hi>Africk,</hi> accuſing both Gods and Men, with imprecations on themſelves for any omiſſions of their own; but truly did ſeverely repine at the Kings ingratitude to (as I may call us) the Nurſes and Fathers of his Country, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> being by his <hi>Father</hi> and all the Inhabitants generally ſo acknowledged; and not undeſervedly, having by their Trade en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich'd it, and brought it to what it was. And ſo great was our rage againſt the <hi>Dutch,</hi> as had our power been conſonant to our will, I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident ſhould have treated them much worſe than the <hi>Javas.</hi> Since our departure, they have had ſome Skirmiſhes with the Old Kings people; with the loſs thereby and Sickneſs (as is report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) 7 or 800 White Men, as yet have not been able to proceed further than the <hi>Fort</hi> and <hi>Town</hi> of <hi>Bantam.</hi> But their Ships being now arrived from <hi>Europe</hi> with a ſupply of near 1000 freſh Souldiers, 'tis reported they deſign ſpeedily to March for <hi>Tertiaſſa</hi> the Reſidence of the Old King, about 20 Miles diſtant from <hi>Bantam:</hi> What their ſucceſs will be time will ſhew. By
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109803:10"/>Sea the Old Kings Forces has done them ſeveral Damages, taken 16 or 17 Sloops and small Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and 'tis ſaid burnt a Ship of near 800 Tons; ſo that they are forced to ſend <hi>Convoys</hi> with their <hi>Fleet</hi> of ſmall Veſſels to and from the Coaſt of <hi>Java.</hi> But leaving them to their Hoſtility a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt each other, I ſhall proceed to a ſhort Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of our Treatment ſince our Arrival here, where as I ſaid we had liberty to hire an Houſe. But as to Matters of Trade were deferr'd An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and that for nigh four Months, the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral telling us every time we came into his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence we ſhould have Anſwer ſometimes to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, ſometimes in few days; and this they did to perplex and intreague our Affairs, having, Ships arrived from <hi>Europe,</hi> deſigned for the Northward, that required a ſpeedy diſpatch, and till received an Anſwer, were not permitted to bring any Goods on ſhore, neither ſuffered they any of their people to go on board us: ſo that we were forced to put Goods from one Ship to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in order to diſpatching them, with ſo much trouble as can ſcarce be imagined, and at laſt (<hi>Eymay</hi> being loſt) ſent two for <hi>Canton,</hi> one for <hi>Tywan,</hi> one for <hi>Tonkeene,</hi> and the <hi>Oacklander</hi> making a 9 Months paſſage, with the loſs of all her Men but 7, was thereby diſabled from proceeding to <hi>Canton,</hi> and forced with moſt black. Saylors to go for <hi>Surrat</hi> in Company with the <hi>Return:</hi> At laſt comes an Anſwer to our ſeveral Letters and Requeſts, that in this long Attendance we had preſented to the General and Council. The Contents are too tedious to recite, but conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109803:10"/>with an Order to us, our Reſidence here not conſiſting with their Intereſt, with all poſſible ſpeed to with-draw our Ships and all our people to ſome of our own ſettled Factories, as <hi>Siam, Surrat, Perſia,</hi> the Coaſt of <hi>Cormandell, Bangall,</hi> or where we thought beſt, and the Seaſon of the year would beſt permit, except all parts belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the King of <hi>Bantam,</hi> who they ſaid had for a reciprocal kindneſs, by Contract made over all his Terretories to them; ſtiling the Old King his Father a Rebel againſt him: by which means there was no place left for us in theſe parts, where we could attend the Arrival of our <hi>Europe</hi> or Northward Ships, till the Company were made ſenſible of the loſs of <hi>Bantam,</hi> and had taken ſome Order about their Affairs in theſe parts. This was a pretty unexpected Story indeed, which made us laugh, but on the wrong ſide of our Mouths, as the Saying is. The Companies Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs and our own too highly requiring our long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſtay here, we were forced to give Anſwer to their Letter more modeſtly than we ſhould o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe have done; repreſenting the unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble damage will occurr to our Maſters Affairs, by their forcing us off; humbly Requeſting per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to abide here till they were acquainted in what condition their Trade in theſe parts was, and had taken ſome Order thereabout; to which as yet we have received no Anſwer, and have hopes they will not urge our departure. If they do, we muſt do as well as we can, we are bound to ſee it, and to ſit dovvn and repine at our Infelici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, vvill not help us. But the Seaſon is novv
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109803:11"/>ſo far ſpent, that if ſo, <hi>England</hi> of neceſſity muſt be our next Port, unleſs we can find ſome place in the Streight of <hi>Sundy</hi> to ſhelter our ſelves. In the mean time we ſit idle, and unable to turn a Penny; the time of our abode here, is ſo much time wholly loſt: For my particular, could my Affairs have permitted, I ſhould have return'd to you by this Ship; but having the Books of the Charge I had in <hi>Bantam</hi> to make up, and my Stock all abroad, that it cannot be in readineſs till the latter Ship, which may depart about <hi>January</hi> next; when if I can be permitted, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign home. The laſt thing I have to adviſe you, is the loſs of the <hi>Johanna,</hi> bound for <hi>Bangall,</hi> who run aſhore in the Night upon a Ridge of Rocks, between the Cape of <hi>Good Hope,</hi> and Cape <hi>Agullis,</hi> where in 12 hours time ſhe broke in two pieces; 'twas about two Miles diſtant from the ſhore, where all the Men but ſeven arrived, ſome in Boats, ſome on Rafts, ſome on the Rack of the Ship, but were 21 days travelling before they arrived where the <hi>Dutch</hi> Inhabited; they all came from <hi>Batavia</hi> in <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships, and the Captain and ſome others take their paſſage home in this Ship. The Company loſt 72000 <hi>l.</hi> Sterling Treaſure, beſide other Merchandize.</p>
               <p>I fear you will think me ſomewhat tedious in relating theſe ſad and tragical Stories, but I was willing to give you a full Relation of all Occurrances. I could wiſh the Subject had been more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and leſs tragical; but we muſt ſubmit to the Divine Will.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours <hi>E. G.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p n="1">I. A Moſt Learned Treatiſe, Entituled, <hi>Fundamental Law the true Security of Sovereign Dignity, and the Peoples Liberty.</hi> By a Perſon of Honour. <hi>Octavo.</hi> Price, One Shilling ſix pence.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The <hi>Romiſh Maſs-Book,</hi> faithfully Tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh</hi> with Notes and Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereupon plainly Demonſtrating the Idolatry and Blaſphemy thereof: Containing, 1. The <hi>Cautelae,</hi> or Cavears of the Maſs. 2. The Canon of the Masſ. 3. The Hiſtory of the Maſs; ſhewing when, how, and by whom it was patched together; with a Curious Copper Cut prefixed, repreſenting the Prieſt ſaying Maſs; with unanſwerable Arguments proving it no Service of God: Publiſhed at this juncture to Prevent the Deſigns of thoſe that are Endeavouring to Introduce <hi>Popery</hi> amongſt us: Dedicated to the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>Henry,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>London.</hi> Price One Shilling.</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>Vates Aſtrologicus,</hi> or <hi>Englands Aſtrological Prophet,</hi> Foretelling what is likely to befall <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> particularly the Great and Famous City of <hi>London,</hi> as alſo <hi>France, Holland, Spain, Germany, Poland, Italy, Sicily, Apulia, Bohemia, Turky,</hi> and indeed all <hi>Europe,</hi> but more eſpecially the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> for twenty years together, beginning <hi>March</hi> 10. 1683. Ending <hi>March.</hi> 10. 1702. likewiſe <hi>Aſtrological Judgments</hi> of the Effects of that famous Triple Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> being thrice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated in that Regal ſign <hi>Leo;</hi> the Great Dignities of the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Jupiter:</hi> alſo ſome Remarks upon the Eclipſes, and more eſpecially upon that great and famous viſible E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe of the Sun, <hi>July</hi> 2d. 1684 with twenty years Predictions from ſome of the moſt Eminent mutual Aſpects of the Planets: and Eclipſes of the Luminaries, and Annual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions of the Sun: with many <hi>Hieroglyphicks,</hi> repreſenting the future State and Chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the world: By <hi>Richard Kirby</hi> Student in Aſtrology. Price One Shilling.</p>
            <p>All Sold by <hi>Thomas Malthus,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Sun</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
